Preliminary Guide to the Otis Graham Jr. papers, 1978-2008 MS2263
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Otis Graham Jr. papers
1978-2008
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Graham, Otis L
MS2263
9 Linear Feet 18 document boxes
This collection contains newspaper articles, policy papers, meeting minutes and correspondence related to the subject of immigration and more specifically the topic of immigration in California. The creator of the collection, Otis Graham Jr., served on the boards of both the Federation for American Immigration Reform (FAIR) and the Center for Immigration Studies (CIS). Some of the records in this collection relate to the work of these two organizations. The material dates from 1978-2008.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Otis Graham, Jr., 2008 (Accession 2009.009).
Biography
Otis L. Graham, Jr., was born in 1935. He is an historian who spent most of his teaching life at the University of California, Santa Barbara. In 1978, he was a member of the founding board of the Federation for American Immigration Reform and served on the Board from more than 20 years. He has also served as Chair and a member of the Board of the Center for Immigration Studies (CIS). Graham has authored or edited numerous books and articles on the subjects of American reform movements, political economy, and environment and immigration. He is the author of a memoir titled Immigration Reform and America's Unchosen Future. This memoir has an insiders perspective of the social movement that challenged the mass immigration movement it identified as forming in the 1960s.
He was a Guggenheim Fellow, a Fellow at the Woodrow Wilson Center for Scholars, the National Endowment for the Humanities, and the Center for Advanced Study and Behavioral Sciences, and received the Robert Kelley Memorial Award from the National Council on Public History.
Graham is a graduate of Yale University (B.A., 1957) and Columbia University (PhD, 1966).
Arrangement
This collection is minimally processed. The documents are maintained in the order received by the donor which had a loose organization by topic and within a topic the papers were loosly organized chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
The two documents in Folder 10a of Box 2 titled "E-mail and memo regarding the FAIR Board" are closed (and have been removed and replaced with a separation sheet) to research unless permission is granted by Otis Graham. Following the death of Otis Graham the documents will remain closed for ten years. During this ten-year period permission to use may be granted by the Chairman of the Board of FAIR. Following this ten-year period the documents will be open to to the public.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains newspaper articles, journal articles, newsletters, organization's publications, correspondence, and meeting minutes related to the topic of immigration. These papers are a mixture of print media and scholarly policy papers reporting upon and exploring immigration from the late 1970s through 2008. These papers were gathered and maintained by Otis Graham and particularly the documents he saved to assist him in writing his memoir. The papers include some records of the organizations the Federation for American Immigration Reform (FAIR), the Center for Immigration Studies (CIS) as well as several grassroots reform organizations. Much of this data appears to relate to the state of California in its immigration debate.
Please note that these papers are not processed and will take more time to use for research. Since these are the records Graham used to write his book some folder titles are actually notes to himself about the chapter that is appropriate for these documents or whether the materials were used in the book. Graham had assigned the original boxes a very broad topic such as Proposition 187 or Immigration trends and patterns. When applicable this box description was added to the folder title. In the absence of meaningful folder titles the box title was used as the folder title. As this collection is still unprocessed it does sometimes result in a folder title that is not paticularly descriptive. This is something that will be rectified when the collection is processed.
Population; Immigration; Immigration opponents -- California; Immigration policy and research; Immigration opponents; Graham, Otis L; Federation for American Immigration Reform; Center for Immigration Studies (Washington, D.C.)
- FAIR founding: Fair Board, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- FAIR founding: Immigration Reform Group, 11/1978-02/28/1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- FAIR founding: On amnesty I and R Commission, 06/09/1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- FAIR founding, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- FAIR founding: SOS Select Commission on Immigration and Refugee Policy, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- FAIR founding, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- FAIR founding, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- FAIR founding: FAIR pamphlet #3, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- FAIR founding: FAIR Survey, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- FAIR founding, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- FAIR founding, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Scope and Contents
  The title of the folder is not legible.
- FAIR founding, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- FAIR founding: FAIR Board records, circa 1982- circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- FAIR founding: FAIR history project, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- FAIR founding: ACRRO, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- FAIR founding, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- FAIR founding, circa 1980- circa 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- FAIR founding: FAIR 10th anniversary, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- FAIR founding: timeline, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- FAIR founding: Board trip, 01/1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- FAIR founding: Board meeting, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- FAIR founding: data from FAIR board books, circ 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- FAIR founding, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- E-mail and memo regarding FAIR Board, 07/15/1989-02/03/2002 (Box 2, Folder 10a, Box R1, Folder 1)
  Restriction
  The e-mail and the memo in this folder have been removed and replaced with a separation sheet explaining the restriction. These documents are closed unless the patron receives permission from Otis Graham to access. Following the death of Otis Graham these documents will remain closed for an addition ten-year period. During this ten-year period permission to use will be granted by the Chairman of the Board of FAIR. Following this ten-year period the documents will be open for research.
- Proposition 187: grassroots, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Proposition 187: Immigration law (Morrison Bill), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Proposition 187 California, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Proposition 187: Calif US Immigration, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Proposition 187, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Proposition 187: FAIR Board, circa 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Proposition 187:, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Proposition 187:, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Proposition 187: Californians for Population Stabilization, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Proposition 187: CA Talk Immigration, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Proposition 187: anti-PC, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Proposition 187: Authur Schlesinger Jr., undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Proposition 187, 10/1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Proposition 187: cult war digest, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- CA Proposition 187, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- CA Proposition 187, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- CA Proposition 187: events, 1998-2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- CA Proposition 187: FAIR, 2001-2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Stein Interview FAIR field, circa 1980- circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- FAIR Field Operations, circa 1980- circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- FAIR Field Operations, 1980-1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- FAIR Field Operations, circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Pickus, 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Pickus citizenship, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Identity Pickus WWWC Project, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- FAIR field operations, 1990-1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- FAIR field operations, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- FAIR field operations, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- FAIR field operations, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- asylum mess of 1990s, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- FAIR misc printed, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Immigration Reform Awareness week, 04/23/1998-04/25/1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- FAIR printed materials, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Biblio, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Growth in California: Growth and Sprawl and the lack of an [illegible] connection, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Growth in California, circa 1990- circa 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Growth in California: CIS next meeting, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Growth in California, circa 1990-2007 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Growth in California, circa 1990-2007 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Growth in California, circa 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Growth in California, circa 1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Growth in California, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Growth in California: scope, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Growth in California: typing notes, 1996-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Growth in California, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  note on file stating "file not used"
- Growth in California, 1997-2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Growth in California, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  note on file "add to ch 25"
- Growth in California: misc to be considered, 01/04/2003 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Growth in California, circa 1990-2007 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Growth in California: immigration, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Growth in California: immigration, 1997-2006 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Growth in California: immigration, 03/2007-04/2007 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Growth in California, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Growth in California, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Immigration, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Immigration, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Jordan Commission, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Immigration, 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Immigration, 2003-2004 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Sierra Club, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Immigration, 1997-2004 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Immigration, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Immigration, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Immigration, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Center for Immigration Studies, 1986-2001 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 1993-1999 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 1995-1998 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 1998-2000 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2001-2003 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2004-2006 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2001-2007 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2002-2003 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2202-2007 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Center for Immigration Studies Publications, 2006-2007 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2005-2006 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Immigration policy and patterns: 90s outlines, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  note on folder "not used in '06"
- Immigration policy and patterns [1/2], 2006 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Immigration policy and patterns [2/2], 2006 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Immigration policy and patterns [1/2], 2006 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Immigration policy and patterns [2/2], 2006 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Immigration policy and patterns Arizona, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2006 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Immigration policy and patterns: no American union, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Immigration policy and patterns: Danish cartoon and Islam, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Immigration policy and patterns, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  note on file " not used"
- Policy wars and immigration trends [1/2], 2005 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  note on file "used"
- Policy wars and immigration trends [2/2], 2005 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Policy wars and immigration trends [1/2], 2006 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Policy wars and immigration trends [2/2], 2006 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Policy wars and immigration trends [1/2], 2006 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Policy wars and immigration trends [2/2], 2006 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2007 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2007 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2007 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2008 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Policy wars and immigration trends [1/2], 2008 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Policy wars and immigration trends [2/2], 2008 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2000-2006 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  Folder had note "misc for review"
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 1997-2008 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  folder had note "Conclusion notes"
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 2005 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  Folder title had note "used for ch 25"
- Policy wars and immigration trends, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  Folder had note "Ch 28"
- Policy wars and immigration trends, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  Folder title had note "Ch 29 not used"
- policy wars and immigration trends, 2008 (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Policy wars and immigration trends, 1998-2006 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  Folder had note "used to revise"
- Policy wars and immigration trends, undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  Folder title had note "to add"